Register of the Winifred V. Ramplee-Smith Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Winifred V. Ramplee-Smith collection,
1915-1917
63011
Ramplee-Smith, Winifred V., collector
1 manuscript box, 1 oversize box (1.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, and postcards, relating to the February 1917 Revolution in Russia. Includes fragments of burned records of the tsarist secret police (Okhrana).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1963.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Scope and Content Note
The Winifred V. Ramplee-Smith collection consists mainly of printed matter relating to the outbreak of the February Revolution in Petrograd and Moscow. It includes anti-monarchist propaganda booklets, revolutionary leaflets and wall-posters. Of special interest are rare copies of contemporary newspapers, including, Izvestiia, Novoe Vremia, and Vestnik Vremennago Pravitel'stva. Also of interest are photographs depicting leaders of the Provisional Government and scenes of the revolution.
Winifred V. Ramplee-Smith was secretary to Lord Templewood and subsequently to Sir Samuel Hoare in Petrograd from 1916-1917. She was in Moscow when the revolution broke out and began collecting printed matter related to the events she witnessed.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Russia. Okhrannye otdeleniia.; Secret service--Russia.; Russia.; Russia--History--February Revolution, 1917.
Series Description
- Biographical File, n.d. (Box 1)
  Visiting card
- Subject File, 1917. (Box 1)
  Fragment of burnt Okhrana record and essay re Russian political parties by Sir Samuel Hoare(?)
- Printed Matter, 1917. (Box 1)
  Revolutionary booklets of popular propaganda; clippings from British newspapers; issue of The New Europe; political leaflets, and military orders. Arranged by physical form and therein chronologically
- Photographs, 1917. (Box 2)
  23 prints depicting members of the Provisional Government and individuals related to the events of 1917, and revolutionary street scenes. Also includes 15 postcards on revolutionary themes
- Oversize File, 1916-1917. (Box 3)
  Newspaper issues published under the Provisional Government and revolutionary wall posters
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, n.d. (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Visiting card, Winifred V. Ramplee-Smith, n.d.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1917
  - Russia. Okhrannyia otdeleniia. (Folder 1: 2)
    Fragment of burnt Okhrana record from a bonfire in Petrograd, 1917 March
  - Political Parties - Russia. (Folder 1: 3)
    Essay by Sir Samuel Hoare (?), entitled "Russian Parties," n.d. Typescript
- PRINTED MATTER, 1917
  - Booklets
    - Author unknown, Politicheskiia pesni svobody, Petrograd, 1917 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Kobyl'-Bobyl', I., Tsaritsa i Rasputin, Petrograd, n.d. (Folder 1: 5)
    - Zhdanov, Lev, Sud nad Nikolaem II, Petrograd, n.d. (Folder 1: 6)
  - Clippings of British newspapers., See also OVERSIZE FILE
    - General, 1917 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Britannia, 1918 August. (Folder 1: 8)
      Front page with photo of Mariia Bochkareva
  - Journal, The New Europe, 1917 February-March (Folder 1: 9)
  - Leaflets., See also OVERSIZE FILE/Wall posters
    - Partiia Narodnoi Svobody, election campaign, n.d. (Folder 1: 10)
    - Polovtsov, Major-General, order to residents of Petrograd, 1917 June 4 (Folder 1: 11)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1917 (Box 2)
  - 2 prints depicting Mariia Bochkareva and her Woman's Battalion, n.d. (Folder 2: 1)
  - 1 print depicting Aleksandr Guchkov, n.d. (Folder 2: 2)
  - 1 print depicting Prince Iusupov and Grand Duchess Irina Aleksandrovna, n.d. (Folder 2: 3)
  - 1 print depicting Aleksandr Kerensky, n.d. (Folder 2: 4)
  - 4 prints and 1 postcard depicting Grigorii Rasputin, n.d. (Folder 2: 5)
  - 1 print depicting Mikhail Rodzianko, n.d. (Folder 2: 6)
  - 1 print depicting Leo Tolstoy at Iasnaia Poliana, n.d. (Folder 2: 7)
  - 15 postcards depicting revolutionary themes, 1917 (Folder 2: 8)
  - 1 print depicting members of the Provisional Government, 1917 (Folder 2: 9)
  - 10 prints depicting revolutionary scenes, 1917 (Folder 2: 10)
  - 1 negative re elections to the Provisional Government, 1917 (Folder 2: 11)
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1917 (Box 3)
  - Newspapers
    - Izvestiia Petrogradskago soveta rabochikh i soldatskikh deputatov, 1917 March 4-5, No. 5-6
    - Novoe Vremia, 1916 November and 1917 April
    - Russkoe Slovo, 1917 October 1
    - Vestnik Vremennago Pravitel'stva, 1917 March 5, no. I
  - Wall posters
    - Biulleten' Revoliutsii: Moskva, 1-go. Marta, 1917.
      Issued by Ispolnitel'naia komissiia vremennago Revoliutsionnago Komiteta, Moskva, Gorodskaia Duma
    - Otchet: Skol'ko promotal i propil za svoe tsarstvovanie narodnykh deneg byvshii tsar' Nikolai Poslednii, n.d.